Guide to the Diego Cortez Mudd Club Collection, circa 1977-1979.
Cortez, Diego Mudd Club Collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Diego Cortez Mudd Club Collection, circa 1977-1979.
8117
Cortez, Diego
.1
Printed materials, photographs, newspapers, audio recordings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The collection features material focused on Cortez's activities as co-founder and manager of the Mudd Club, 1977-1979, with items by or relating to artists with whom he collaborated, such as Jimmy de Sana, Arto Lindsay, Kathy Acker, James Nares and Boris Policeband, and Diego's original artwork for the seminal "No New York" (1978) LP. There are 7 black and white photographs (5x7) by Digne Meller Marcovicz taken around Diego's film "Grutzi Elvis" shot in Germany (1978), 11 black and white silver gelatin photographs by Jimmy de Sana, 8 Polaroids by Diego Cortez, two notebooks relating to the band Boris Policeband, 26 flyers and zines (including some original paste-ups) and 3, 7" 45rpm records in picture sleeves for the bands DNA, Teenage Jesus & the Jerks, and Boris Policeband.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Born James Allen Curtis in Geneva, Illinois in 1946, Curtis moved to New York City in 1973 and assumed the name Diego Cortez. He became well-known as an artist, club manager, promoter, and independent curator, co-founding the influential NYC nightspot The Mudd Club, which offered an eclectic mix of art, music and cultural events that combined both modernist and punk aesthetics. The Mudd Club operated at 77 White Street in downtown Manhattan between 1978 and 1983. In 1981, Cortez curated the groundbreaking exhibition "New York, No Wave" at a defunct elementary school in Long Island City, Queens called P.S. 1. The exhibition featured the work of David Byrne, Keith Haring, Robert Mapplethorpe, Jean-Michel Basquiat, and Kenny Scharf, among many others.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection features material focused on Cortez's activities as co-founder and manager of the Mudd Club, 1977-1979, with items by or relating to artists with whom he collaborated, such as Jimmy de Sana, Arto Lindsay, Kathy Acker, James Nares and Boris Policeband, and Diego's original artwork for the seminal "No New York" (1978) LP. There are 7 black and white photographs (5x7) by Digne Meller Marcovicz taken around Diego's film "Grutzi Elvis" shot in Germany (1978), 11 black and white silver gelatin photographs by Jimmy de Sana, 8 Polaroids by Diego Cortez, two notebooks relating to the band Boris Policeband, 26 flyers and zines (including some original paste-ups) and 3, 7" 45rpm records in picture sleeves for the bands DNA, Teenage Jesus & the Jerks, and Boris Policeband.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cortez, Diego,; Acker, Kathy, 1948-1997; De Sana, Jimmy.
Subjects:
Nightclubs.; Nightlife.; Punk culture.; Punk rock music.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Due to the fragility and potential degradation of moving image and sound recordings, viewing and listening is limited to items that have been digitized. If an item is in another media format, you may request to have the item digitized for access. Information on ordering access copies may be found on our Reproductions and Permissions page.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Photographs
  - Digne Meller Marcovicz photographs, 1978; Marcovicz, Digne Meller (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Taken around filming of "Grutzi Elvis" in Munich and Darmstadt, Germany
  - Jack Smith, film maker, 1970's; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diego Cortez, 1979; Resnick, Marcia (Box 1, Folder 1)
    After an incident outside of a Tribeca night club where Cortez was punched and had his nose bloodied
  - Diego Cortez, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Still from "Grutzi Elvis"
  - Diego Cortez and Anya Phillips, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Publicity still from "Grutzi Elvis"
  - Jimmy de Sana photographs
    - David Byrne, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Backstage at The Bottom Line, NYC
    - Debbie Harry and Diego Cortez, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Richard Hell and Anya Phillips, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
      At Micky Ruskin's Lower Manhattan Ocean Club
    - James Nares and Diego Cortez, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Chinatown, NYC
    - Patti Smith, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
      On stage with guitar
    - Patti Smith, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
      In performance, hands on stomach
    - Richard Hell, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Smoking backstage
    - Julia Heyward, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
      At home
    - Seth Tillett, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - David Byrne, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Headshot, singing, microphone
    - David Byrne, 1978-1979; de Sana, Jimmy (Box 1, Folder 1)
      At Jimmy de Sana's loft.
  - Diego Cortez polaroids
    - Glenn Mercer (4), 1978-1979; Cortez, Diego (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Lead vocalist and guitarist of The Feelies
    - Anna Sui, 1978-1979; Cortez, Diego (Box 1, Folder 1)
      At CBGB's
    - Michael Cooper, Jimmy DeSana and Ray Johnson, 1978-1979; Cortez, Diego (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified (2), 1978-1979; Cortez, Diego (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. Notebooks
  - Boris Policeband notebook I, 1979-03-11; Cortez, Diego (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Outlining performance at The Mudd Club, annotations in Cortez's hand
  - Boris Policeband notebook II, 1979-30-1979-05; Cortez, Diego (Box 1, Folder 2)
    New York performances and others, annotations in Cortez's hand
- Series III. Flyers/Posters/Zines
  - Postcard announcing "The Batman Show", 1979-01-06, 1979-01-13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Zerox & Blood, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Exhibition at The Whitney Museum Art Resources Center
    Xerox flyer
  - DNA (2), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Live at Max's Kansas City
  - DNA, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Live at CBGB
  - MARS/DNA, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - James Chance and The Contortions, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Live at Max's Kansas City, includes annotations by Diego Cortez
  - Policeband, 1979-03-11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    At the Mudd Club with opening act Suzuki Class
  - Tuesday Night, 1977-09-20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tuesday Night #5, 1977-09-27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes reviews of shows
    Xerox zine
  - Tuesday Night, 1977-10-04 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Teenage Jesus and The Jerks (2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flyer announcing reading of "Blood and Guts in High School" by Kathy Acker, with Diego Cortez, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    At The Kitchen
  - Flyer announcing various events, 1977Summer 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    At The Kitchen; stapled with additional list on yellow paper
  - Paste-up of flyer announcing various Diego Cortez events, 1977-01-25-1977-01-31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    At Anthology Film Archives, NYC
  - Flyer, "Medical Records", Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Original text scribbled over with pen
  - Flyer, "Studies for Grutzi Elvis", Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Original mockup
  - Flyer, "Studies for Grutzi Elvis", Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flyer, Richard Lloyd Jam/video/Diego Cortez, 1978-06 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Max's
  - Image of Hans Magnus Enzensberger, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - An Evening Commemorating Zanu's, 1979-05-17 (Folder 1)
    Flyer advertising performance by Policeband and Beirut Slump at the Mudd Club
  - Yellow flyer, "No New York", 1978Spring 1978 (Folder 1)
  - Mockup of soundtrack album cover, Undated (Folder 1)
  - Flyer, "Television Talking Heads", Undated (Folder 1)
  - Poster announcing "Bands at Artists Space", Undated (Folder 1)
  - X Magazine, Undated (Folder 1)
    Volume 2, issue 4-6
- Series IV. Records
  - "Orphans b/w Less of Me", 1978; SR-20357; Teenage Jesus & The Jerks (Box 1, Folder 5)
    45 rpm
  - "You & You blw Little Ants", 1978; SR-20358; DNA (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Back cover photo by Diego Cortez
  - "Stereo/Mono", 1979; SR-20359; Policeband (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Accompanied Boris Policeband notebook I; inscribed on front and back cover by Diego Cortez